Eugene St. Pierre Papers 1986.0007
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Eugene St. Pierre Papers
1933-1974
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1986.0007
7 Linear Feet
Eugene St. Pierre was a prominent labor leader in the Hartford area from 1955 to 1974.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The papers were transferred to the University of Connecticut Archives by the University Foundation in 1986.
Arrangement
Series I: International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) Records (1954-1974) contains records of the national offices of the IBEW. The series consists of correspondence, health and pension benefits information, surveys, newsletters, charter and by-law instructions, as well as weekly and financial reports. There is also correspondence with John Flynn, the international vice-president for the New England area and St. Pierre's immediate supervisor.
Series II: IBEW Local Union Records (1933-1974) contains material exchanged by the local unions for which St. Pierre, as one of the eight international representatives for New England, was responsible. Included are correspondence, newsletters, election results, membership and officer lists, information on dues, records and notes concerning contract disputes and agreements, and other paperwork related to local union activity. The minutes, officers' lists, by-laws, benefits, and dues for Local 1013, of which St. Pierre was a member, are included for 1933 to 1974.
Series III: Labor Organizations (1933-1974) contains material regarding labor organizations which St. Pierre dealt with or was a member of, including the Connecticut Labor Department, the Connecticut State Labor Council, the Committee on Political Education, the Greater Hartford Labor Council, the Connecticut AFL-CIO and Rhode Island AFL-CIO, the U.S. Department of Labor, and the National Labor Relations Board. This series also contains pay rate comparisons for various industries in Connecticut between 1933 and 1967.
Series IV: Personal Papers (1934-1974) contains information about local and state organizations with which St. Pierre was associated throughout his career. These include the Community Renewal Team of Hartford, the >Connecticut Marketing Authority, the Hartford YMCA, and the Urban Policy Conference Program. In addition, this series contains personal correspondence, newsletters, and a collection of memorabilia such as convention ribbons and souvenirs, newspaper clippings, photographs, business cards, union ballots, and personal documents.
Biography
Eugene St. Pierre was a prominent labor leader in the Hartford area from 1955 to 1974. St. Pierre, who worked for the Arrow-Hart & Hageman Corporation of Hartford for twenty-seven years, rose through the ranks of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Union Local 1013 to eventually become its president. He was one of the original founding members of the local when it was organized in 1933. Over the years he served the union in various capacities as steward, recording secretary, financial secretary, and executive board member.
In 1955, St. Pierre was appointed an international representative for the IBEW; a position he held until his retirement in 1974. As international representative, he was responsible for union organizing and collective bargaining activities in southeastern New England. He was also president of the Greater Hartford Labor Council in the late 1950s and early 1960s.
Besides being active in many labor organizations, St. Pierre was also involved in many local and state activities. He served on the State Development Commissions during the Administration of Governor Chester Bowles>, and he was also a member of the board of directors for the Hartford YMCA for many years.
He died in 1986 at the age of 78.
Custodial History
The Eugene St. Pierre Papers were donated to the University of Connecticut Foundation by the estate of Eugene St. Pierre in May 1986.
Scope and Content
The papers of Eugene St. Pierre provide the researcher with a close up and intimate view of labor activities on the local level. In addition, they provide a detailed record of the state of the Connecticut economy and its effect on blue-collar workers from 1955 to 1974. Documents in the collection include correspondence, reports, surveys, newsletters, financial and administrative records, minutes, and ephemera.
Electric industries; Notes; Photocopies; Electricians; Fliers (printed matter); Minutes (administrative records); United States (nation); Labor; Financial Records; Connecticut (state); Labor unions; Administrative records; Hartford (inhabited place); Political participation; Labor leaders; Correspondence; Photographs; Publications (documents); AFL-CIO. Greater Hartford Labor Council; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers
- Series I: IBEW Records, 1954-1974
  - Benefits: hospitalization, pensions, death, workmen's compensation, 1954-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Convention roll call of delegates, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial reports, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
  - John Flynn correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - Procedures concerning civil rights acts, reports, charters, and promotional activities, 1956-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Surveys, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Weekly reports, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19-23)
- Series II: IBEW Local Union Records, 1933-1974
  - 255, Jewett City, CT, Plastic Wire & Cable Co., 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 410, New Bedford, MA, Cornell-Dubillier Co., 1957-1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 437, Fall River, MA, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 977, Meriden, CT, The Miller Co., 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1013, Winsted, CT, Dano-Electric Co., 1933-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
  - 1040, East Hartford, CT, Wiremold Co., 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
  - 1069, Stamford, CT, Marchand Co., 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1098, Pawtucket, RI, Collyer Co., 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
  - 1267, Waltham, MA, New England Mica Co., 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1268, Boston, MA, Frank P. Morse Co., 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 1274, Warwick, RI, Leviton Co., 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 42-46)
  - 1444, Providence, RI, Cable Electric Co., 1958-1974 (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
  - 1754, North Dartmouth, MA, Aluminum Processing Co. and Aerovox Co., 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
  - 2255, Fall River, MA, Aluminum Processing Co., 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 52-54)
  - 2275, Winsted, CT, Dano Electric Co. and Arrow-Hart & Hagemen Co., 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 55-57)
- Series III: Labor Organizations, 1933-1974
  - Committee on Political Education, AFL-CIO: newsletters, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
  - Connecticut Labor Department, 1968-1973
    - Labor situations (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Trends in unemployment (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Labor turnover (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Hartford Labor Market Letter (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - New manufacturing firms (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Connecticut State Labor Council, AFL-CIO: Bulletins, newsletters, correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
  - Greater Hartford Labor Council, AFL-CIO: Meetings, minutes, by-laws, 1960-1974 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Handbills: Organizing for the IBEW and AFL-CIO, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Pay rates, male and female labor: Various jobs and companies, 1933-1967 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Rhode Island AFL-CIO: newsletters and correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - U.S. Department of Labor: newsletters and studies, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - U.S. National Labor Relations Board: Correspondence, voting procedures and tallies, Forms, employee voting lists, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 72)
- Series IV: Personal Papers, 1934-1974
  - Community Renewal Team of Greater Hartford: action program draft, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Connecticut Marketing Authority: meetings and correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Hartford YMCA: chairman of the Organized Labor Committee, correspondence and newsletters, 1962-1973 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Unidentified correspondence, newsletters, posters, 1962-1973 (Box 4, Folder 76-78)
  - Union leasing records: automobile rentals, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Urban Policy Conference Program: Advanced study program, "Greater Hartford And Its Future", 1964 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Personal memorabilia: convention ribbons, 1940-1965 (Box 5, Box 6, Box 7)
  - Personal memorabilia: convention ribbons and souvenirs, 1936-1971 (Box 8)
  - Personal memorabilia, 1934-1972 (Box 9)
    - Newspaper clippings
    - Union ballots
    - Photographs
    - Personal documents
    - Unidentified personal items
    - Scrapbook with clippings and business cards